Guide to the Gail and Stephen Rudin New York landmarks collection, 1835-1944.
Rudin, Gail and Stephen Rudin New York landmarks collection
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Gail and Stephen Rudin New York landmarks collection, 1835-1944.
6991
Rudin, Stephen,
.3 cubic feet.
correspondence, printed materials, publications, photographs
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Paper ephemera, postcards, and photographs related to the Brooklyn Bridge and other New York landmarks. Includes booklet, program, invitation, and ticket to opening ceremony for bridge on May 24, 1883. Also includes receipt for the purchase of Randall's Island, as well as miscellany related to the Holland Tunnel and the Statue of Liberty.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Paper ephemera, postcards, and photographs related to the Brooklyn Bridge and other New York landmarks. Includes booklet, program, invitation, and ticket to opening ceremony for bridge on May 24, 1883. Also includes receipt for the purchase of Randall's Island, as well as miscellany related to the Holland Tunnel and the Statue of Liberty.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Rudin, Stephen,
Places:
Brooklyn Bridge (New York, N.Y.); Randalls Island (N.Y.); Holland Tunnel (Jersey City, N.J., and New York, N.Y.); Statue of Liberty National Monument (N.Y. and N.J.); New York (N.Y.) -- History.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Brooklyn Bridge
Series II. Other New York Landmarks
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Brooklyn Bridge
  - Stranahan, James S.T., Pages: 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Signature of the President of Brooklyn Park Board; Father of the Brooklyn Bridge.
    Rudin # M-45A
  - "Pneumatic Tower Foundations of the East River Suspension Bridge", by W.A. Roebling., 1872 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    With folding plates.
    Rudin # M-46
  - Opening day souvenir booklet., 1883 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Rudin # M-47
  - Brooklyn Bridge pass, April 21, 1883; ADS (Box 1, Folder 4)
    "Pass the bearer and friends over the Bridge at all times", signed by William Kingsley.
    Rudin # M-47A
  - Opening ceremonies program, May 24, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    "Opening Ceremonies of New York and Brooklyn Bridge" - Program. With Brooklyn Bridge First Day Cover and Brooklyn Bridge Maximum Card.
    Rudin # M-48
  - Official invitation for the Opening Ceremonies of the New York and Brooklyn Bridge., May 24, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Rudin # M-49
  - Ticket to the Opening Ceremonies of the New York and Brooklyn Bridge., May 24, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Rudin # M-50
  - Advertising envelope with engraving of Brooklyn Bridge., September 13, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Rudin # M-51A
  - Newspaper, May 25, 1883 (Folder 1)
    "The Herald" - Omaha: "Brooklyn's Bridge. Opening of the New Link Between the Two Great Cities…" Describes festivities and political events surrounding the opening.
    Rudin # M-51
  - Two albumen photos of the Brooklyn Bridge., ca. 1880s (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Rudin # M-52B
  - Six New York and Brooklyn Bridge railroad and promenade tickets (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Rudin # M-53
  - Roebling letterhead, August 13, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Ornate pictorial letterhead (of Brooklyn Bridge) with stylized typography, including Roebling correspondence regarding legal matters. Signed in type.
    Rudin # M-53A
  - Five philatelic envelopes and one woodcut relating to the Brooklyn Bridge. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Rudin # M-54A
  - Magnus print of "New York, Brooklyn and Williamsburg". (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Rudin # M-54B
  - Postcard collection of Brooklyn Bridge images., 1903-1944 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Rudin # M-54C
  - New York City map., 1894 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Map of New York with portions of Brooklyn and Jersey City, including Brooklyn Bridge location.
    Rudin # M-50B
  - Photograph, ca. 1880s (Box 2, Folder 2)
    The "Great Bridge" - Image probably taken soon after bridge was completed.
    Rudin # M-52
  - Panorama viewing set, 1883 (Box 2)
    Box cut with magnifying lens. Contains 11 views of Brooklyn Bridge, etc.
    Rudin # M-50A
  - Engraving, ca. 1883 (Folder 1)
    Period engraving of Brooklyn Bridge soon after it opened.
    Rudin # M-52C
- Series II. Other New York Landmarks
  - Randall's Island purchase, April 23, 1835 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Receipt for the purchase of Randall's Island by the City of New York for $60,000.
    Rudin # M-91
  - Holland Tunnel Invitation, Ticket, and Envelope, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Rudin # M-93
  - Dedicating the Statue of Liberty, October 28, 1886 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Two pieces: Engraved image of the Statue of Liberty inviting the bearer to the inauguration by the President; Rare steamboat ticket for passage and admission to the platform at the event. See also Bartholdi and Pulitzer letters, Rudin #s A-7, A-8, A-8A, and A-191 in the Gail and Stephen Rudin Autograph Collection, collection #6875.
    Rudin # M-103
  - Statue of Liberty stamps and coins (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Folder containing eleven stamps and four coins commemorating the 125th anniversary of the Statue of Liberty.
    Rudin # M-104
SEPARATED MATERIAL
Books
Brooklyn Bridge 1883-1933. A valuable history published to commemorate the 50th anniversary of the Brooklyn Bridge. First Edition.
Opening Ceremonies of the New York and Brooklyn Bridge. 1883. Inscribed on flyleaf by Emily Warren Roebling, wife of Chief Engineer Washington Roebling. Rudin # M-48A
The New York City Subway: Its Construction and Equipment. Inscription reads "Presented to Alderman John H. Dougherty, by August Belmont, Esq. President, Interborough Rapid Transit Company, November 21st, 1904". Rudin # M-94